Hello, I'm Russell Brand. This episode
of Under the Skin from Luminary Media is
free and it's fantastic. It's got Ricky
Jves in it. Ricky Jves, one of the best
comedy stars the world's ever known. I
think it's safe to say he's up there
with your Chaplain, your Cleleses, your
Kugans. They're all British comedians
whose names start with C. That's all I'm
interested. Your cooks, your Hancocks.
Ricky Devase, outspoken host of the
Globes, creator of Extras, The Office
Afterlife, season two of which is on
Netflix now and is the it's because of
him promoting that that he's even come
on our podcast. This is for you for
nothing. But if you want to sign up and
get all of the episodes of Under the
Skin, which let me tell you are worth
it, as well as all the other fantastic
content that's on that platform, podcast
from Komo, from Queer Eye, no content
from uh Lena Dun, get down then. No
one's making you stay here. You're not a
hostage. I'd say this is a fantastic
episode of Under the Skin. I'm very
proud of it. It's a brilliant
conversation with Ricky Jabase. It's a
joy to talk to him. He and me and him as
we discuss see the world somewhat
differently although we've got loads of
things in common. We talk about God,
atheism,
animals, love, class, fantastic stuff.
You'll really, really enjoy it. If you
want to get Luminary, if this episode
indicates to you that these are the kind
of conversations you might be into, then
you can get it for as little as $2.99 a
month with the with the Luminary annual
plan, and you can get a 7-day free
trial, which I would recommend to all of
you. Check out the brilliant podcasts
I've done with well other podcasters
like on the platform like Lena Dunham
and Kuramo, but also David Eagleman,
Neil Degrass, Tyson, Brian Cox, Janice
Farafakis, I mean there's like brilliant
intellectual conversations. Naomi Klene,
I mean it's just like Dr. Shafari last
week talking about I mean I really think
they are valuable conversations but this
one for nothing with Ricky is uh it's
especially good as you would imagine
from Ricky Jace and uh let me reiterate
Afterlife which I've watched is on
Netflix now and it's fantastic. Check it
out.
Hello.
Hello mate. It's so lovely to see you.
Look at you all grown up.
I've become an adult.
Well, I'm I'm relieved you're not sat
there in a sheet.
That was a deal breaker. I said I wanted
to conform to Western ways just for one
hour.
I didn't even need to have that
explicitly explained to me. I s intuited
that it might not be wise to interview
you in a sheet.
And why is it 100 p.m.? I mean, that is
bang on soup and snooze hour for me. I I
have a I have a little lentil soup and
then I have a little nap, right? So, now
I've had to have my soup at half 12.
Gobbled that down. It was very hot and
the my nap is postponed till 2:00 p.m.
So, this is just some of the hardship
that I've been going through during the
pandemic.
It's a a grueling tale even to sit and
listen to Ricky. that kind of suffering.
It's uh like the Goolag archipilago
listening to some of that stuff.
You got a real mic and everything.
Yeah, cuz I do like I've been doing a
podcast for for ages. So, we put one in
the garage like a little podcast studio.
Do you
I went from the only person with a
podcast to the only person without one.
So, I had to go the other way.
You're an outlier, a pioneer, and an
extremist.
I'm a rebel. You know, I've always been
a rebel.
Like Tony Hancock, in fact, just like
Tony Hancock's rebel.
There's no There's no question you're in
that lineage. No question. Do you should
we do this little Should we do this
little interview? Start it officially.
I'll start it with like a compliment to
put you at your ease. It's really lovely
to interview you. I'm I am very nervous.
I can see that your rat.
It might be the soup. I drank too
quickly.
Yeah. Essophical burning and anxiety
have similar symptoms.
Um yeah, it's lovely to have a proper
interview with you. We've had like met a
few times. I've never been able to speak
to you at depth, but like anyone, I
admire you as a comedian very very much.
And I still like watch like a lot of
your stuff like, you know, maybe even
just when you're doing Facebook lives,
but also like I still watch The Office.
I watch Afterlife, checking out the news
series, which is what you're promoting
at the moment, doing these like podcasts
and that. And it's a real joy to talk to
you, Ricky.
Thank you. Same. Same. Pleasure.
Thanks, mate. Um, I suppose like
my compliment was a lot shorter than
yours, wasn't it? I didn't give you much
back. I felt I felt it wasn't the place
cuz I feel like a guest.
You are a guest. You are a guest. And in
a sense, it's proportionate to our BAFTA
backdrops.
You've got endless masks. I've got a
drape.
Let me explain. I've made an effort.
I've put a nice little jumper on. I've
washed and all that. But this is this is
my desk. I'm at my desk. The my my this
is the smallest room in the house cuz I
thought the echo would because the other
rooms are vast and it would be good for
So, okay, this isn't this isn't like
cribs where I've hired them.
I really did win them.
I was watching I was watching I I
remember I remember a good many of them
then for I don't know what that bore is
like there's a wild boar. I guess that's
some sort of writing guild or is it
simply an ornament?
That's a Oh, I'm glad you brought that.
That's a work of art that um I that was
auctioned for charity and I gave so
generously. That reminds me what a great
person I am.
It's good to have a momento of your own
greatness next to those less abstract
accolades.
Good. I live pretty near where you're
from, mate. Like I So I see sort of like
you're from Reading and of course. And
aren't you?
Yeah. Yeah. It's obviously lovely around
here. Do you live near here?
Um well, we've got a little place quite
near you. Um but uh my main I mean I
mean I'm mostly in Leafy Hamstead.
Yeah.
Where people like you aren't allowed if
I'm being honest.
I was there briefly for a while. I lived
on Gardenor Road at what I might call
the height of my decadence. Yeah. Near
Flask Walk and uh
Oh, beautiful. Well, we used to visit
this uh place, you know, before we lived
here. We lived in the center ever since
sort of college. And um uh uh to
explaining to Americans what Hamstead is
like, I I say it's it's sort of bohemian
and eclectic and it's the sort of great
great grandchildren of artists and poets
and me new money. I I always feel that
it was like the Beverly Hillbillies when
I rolled into town.
So, and I think I think I think we're
from similar sort of backgrounds where
we moved where we moved up to be able to
live next door to to wealthy people. So,
I still I still feel when I walk into
the Ivy, there's a certain amount of
disappointment on people's faces.
Yeah. It's incredible actually. And like
it's sort of a very um clear in your
humor that you have that kind of
background. I remember watching Martin
Freeman on something once saying that
you were the first person he'd met that
had a sense of humor that made him laugh
like people at school. And I remember
when I used to when you used to do on
stuff on 11:00 show and you talked about
like I remember in particular one time
when you talked about the apocryful
often
and then opening their eyes and having a
cup of tea there and like I guess this
was probably 20 years ago but I remember
watching that and thinking oh that's
funny man that's funny and I suppose and
you've how how have you maintained and
do you think you've maintained that kind
of access to normality? and that kind of
brittle spiky workingass humor now that
you are in sconced on the hill. Well, I
I think I think I have uh in in many
ways. Um obviously all my family still
live around reading wokenum fat and you
know and they're what you call a working
class. They're all manual workers or
carers and and then there's a there's 50
I haven't counted them sort of great
nieces and nephews that you know. Um,
and so, uh, there there's there's that
where you're always connected to your
family. You always you always feel at
home with your family, you know. Um, uh,
so there's there's that. I I do it I
sort of do it quite consciously try and
remember my roots because as a comedian
um, so professionally I I I I sort of do
as well. I think because we're caught
jesters. We have to be caught jesters.
We have to have low status. We're in the
mud with all the other peasants teasing
the king. Not too much because we don't
want to get killed, but we have to keep
our low status somehow. I think I I feel
I want to. And and I do that in two
ways. And you do this as well. Um one, I
invite them behind the curtain. I go,
"What? You think it's great being rich
and famous? Well, this is what I said in
front of the queen. This is the first
time I got a private jet. They thought I
was the cook." So I So I do that. I give
them the horror stories where I was the
putt. I was the wrong person. I
shouldn't have been there. I tell them
that. And I the other way I do it is I
talk about things where they're better
off than me. I talk about being fat and
old and balding and do you know what I
mean?
Yeah.
So I'm going to die soon. And so you you
do have to particularly when people know
what top comedians earn now. It it's
like um I sort of embraced that as well.
I teased them. I like I did, you know,
like uh talking about house and wealth
in an ironic way and they get that as
well. And I I I'm sort of saying,
listen, this is luck. I do you know what
I mean? This isn't I don't think I
deserve this. Um uh but uh I think
people get it as long as you're honest.
It would it would when if I see a
millionaire comedian going either way uh
either side of that like uh talking down
to an audience that everything's is a is
a battle story that they won or you know
they've already they're already on stage
they're already an expensive suit or
whatever and and now they're telling the
audience that they're wrong. Again I do
that ironically but they get it like a
mate. I call them scum and they they
know they get that I'm saying the
opposite. Um but uh it would be equally
stupid um when I see millionaire
comedians going so I was signing on
yesterday and um I was on the I was on
the bus and no you [__] weren't. No
you weren't. you know, but I usually go
the other way. Like um uh I typical joke
I did in Humanity was um uh press they
always ask, you know, wealthy
entertainers, how much is a pint of
milk? Um that's meant to show you you're
and I then I say I don't know. I haven't
checked. But the next time someone asks
me, I say, I don't know, mate. It is a
grand. Run and get me one. So I I I I
sort of embrace
my privilege um for comic effect. I
think
the first thing that most of us know you
for it couldn't be a clearer
exemplification of authenticity. The
office whether it's the way it was shot,
the way that it was scripted, the kind
of uh acute observation of normality and
mundanity. So like sort of from the
outset there is an authenticity to your
work with something that more recent
like afterlife which I watched as I was
instructed to watch the first couple.
It's brilliant. It's you know it's like
someone told me you got to watch it. I
watched uh one and a half. Do you know
what I mean and like and like it's I've
loved the first series. I think there's
great people in it. I love Roshene. I
love that woman Joe that's in it. I
think it's a really brilliant cast. I
love her that's off of Charlie Brooker's
stuff as well. She's wicked. Obviously,
you're great. Um, like what uh are you
do you have the same level of uh
authenticity and uh sort of I don't know
cander when you're making something like
that? And if so, where are you getting
the stuff about suicide and despair
from?
It's it's it's sort of the only thing I
care about now more and more. Every day
I wake up and I sort of say, um, is this
is this honest enough? Is this more
true? I like I'm peeling away these
layers and going, you know, it sends you
mad because I I I don't feel that I want
to be
more famous or richer or win more
awards. I feel that am I being am I
using my platform to its greatest effect
now? Am I being more honest? Am I
getting everything off my chest before I
die? Am I am I really do I really mean
this? Am I I can only do things that I'm
passionate about because you'll get
caught out. So the answer is yes. And um
the office
um I suppose uh realism was sort of
fortuitous or by accident or or
whatever. Um cuz I worked in an office
for 10 years. So it was harder for me to
get it wrong. You know what I mean?
Because I'm going that wouldn't happen,
that didn't happen, that wouldn't. So
that was easy. I was also emulating
something I it was a it was a fake docu
soap and I'd watched a lot of those
through the 90s where an ordinary person
got their 15 minutes of fame and uh you
know it was interesting just being at
work. So that was the influences. So it
was easy it was easy to make it real and
you know later you find out that we
probably cheated less than real
documentaries particularly by today's
standards. We wouldn't have a camera
waiting for someone. We wouldn't get
them caught doing something unless it
was a really elaborate spy or they
forgot their mic was on. So, um uh I
I've always been obsessed
with um with realism. All the my
favorite things were real. Even
even to the point that um uh well the
first time I saw a Mike Lee thing I'm
sort of I don't know for I just thought
this is I'd never seen this before.
People talking over each other and it
wasn't even intimate. It was a you know
a shoddy old play shot with a few
cameras. It wasn't even as good as he it
became. And even in that even in
Abigail's party which I thought and I
still think is genius. There's one bit
that made me feel guilty that when he
says, and it's a great joke. It's a
great joke. Um, uh, he goes, uh,
Shakespeare, complete works of
Shakespeare, leather bound, and they go,
he's showing up, and he goes, of course,
you couldn't read that sort of thing.
And I sort of thought, well, that's a
snobby joke cuz you know what? Most
people don't. And that's and is that is
that is he taking the piss out of my
tribe that are trying to better
themselves, but not quite get it right.
And there was still a little flitter of,
oh, okay. Okay. So, when I came to do it
myself, I wanted I did want to embrace
that that that sort of honest working
class thing. I wanted a mix like Billy
Connelly. I just thought I wanted to be
like him that he spoke to his crowd like
you do to a mate down a pub. And um uh
and I remember one of my first
uh I had a meeting with uh Channel 4
about the show even before The Office
when I I did um the 11:00 show and uh
and the big thing there was um Chris
Morrison and Brass Eye which I thought I
still think is amazing. Um but it's also
very sort of uh it's very sort of
Guardian, isn't it? It's not like, do
you know what I mean? It's but the
people who love it are and I thought I
want to I want to mix that sort of
comedy and that sort of I suppose
pursuit of excellence and intellect but
make it sort of accessible. And so I
remember I turned the I want to do
um I was I was talking to someone and um
uh I said I sort of want to bring that
to the working classes which sounds very
patronizing
early days but I felt that you know my
family didn't watch Brass Lie. I felt
like I was part of the media loving
something. Do do you know what I mean?
Yeah, I do know what you mean. I
understand the idea of sort of uh
cultural eliteism and esotericism and I
feel like like you know you obviously
have an incredibly refined uh sense of
humor and at the risk of bolstering a
compliment that I've already given you
that was scarcely reciprocated
I feel like you're a genius like like in
a like proper Hancock Clean
kind of lineage and even though your
background is sort of marked by
ordinariness and ordinariness and the
sort of gentle beauty of the ordinary is
obviously something that captivates you
there is something alienating first I
think about that kind of insight that
you have and I and I would offer also
secondarily by becoming very successful
and I I wonder about how you like what
how you've experienced alienation both
prior to success
and subsequent to it also bearing in
mind like you know like prior to your uh
comedy career you know the stuff with
the new romantic looking 20-year-old
Ricky Jay stuff and also remember I did
mention to you about suicide and despair
earlier so if you can just have an
answer that covers all of that
territory. Jesus.
Um, uh, well,
I I don't know if I've I I I don't know.
I don't think I've ever suffered from
any of those more chronic conditions of
I I've never I've never really felt
that alienated or I've never suffered
from terrible anxiety or depression
without cause, you know. I've had I've
had grief
you know, loved ones dying, all that.
Um, uh, growing up, I just, I mean, I
didn't I didn't know I was poor and
working class till I was 14, 15. I
didn't, do you know what I mean? We're
all in the same boat. I went to a
comprehensive school. Um, I was, you
know, I was I was smart, so I was in the
top few there. I always I always felt
I'd go to university. I just that, do
you know what I I never felt
everything's out of my reach. I never
thought
it won't happen to you.
Um, which is odd.
Yeah.
I don't know why I had that confidence.
Maybe I didn't. Maybe I'm remembering it
wrong. Maybe it was bravado.
Or maybe I just thought that's the only
way to do it. Academia.
Um,
uh, it's so funny because, you know, 500
years ago to move through a class, you
know, you had to be a great
warrior and you might get a night but
that was very rare and dangerous. Then
the industrialists started you know
finding coal and or you know prospectors
went and found gold and they moved up
and they moved into neighborhoods like
mine. Um and uh you know they they
became wealthier than the wealthy. But
in our sort of lifetime, it I suppose
the the last group to do it were was
it's pop pop culture, you know, it's
it's it's footballers and pop stars
where, you know, you suddenly heard
workingass and regional accents and they
were in mansion houses and driving
Rolls-Royces into pools, which I'm sure
you've done, but I never would. I'd go,
that's a waste. Let's get you. Um, so,
uh, he's thrown a tally out. We can, we
can fix this. We can fix this.
Um, so I'm sort of aware of all those
things, but I never I never felt it. I
was never conscious of it, you know. I
suppose the first time I went through an
interview at university, that's when I
heard people who sounded a bit like the
queen and I hadn't heard that accent. my
you know my teachers were working class
it was like everything they were working
class they were lads they were working
class lads in a in a comprehensive
school in med um so that's when I you
started mixing with
um people you know of difference uh in
in class and wealth and um I remember
meeting someone he he he didn't know
what a supermarket was and I thought he
was winding me up I thought he was
winding me up. Um, and I guess I I
played it a bit cuz I my first year I I
gave myself a skin head and I loved the
fact that I was IDed going into the
college and I could show my So I I
definitely and I I remember I wore my
dad's old uh lang donkey jacket in Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Hi guys. I'm working class.
I'm one of the 6%. Hi guys.
You know what I mean? It's like
Um but uh what was the last part of the
question? Have I
Well, I guess I was sort of talking
about like you've sort of explained
didn't feel alienated, but like but you
also don't seems like you you wore
literally your class as a badge and
didn't feel inferiority and like I
suppose like you know a character like
David Brent like who's like under all
this sort of excruciating social
pressure and wants to better himself on
camera right through to uh the
protagonist in afterlife dealing with
despair like it's like in your like and
and of of course your obsession with uh
authenticity. I wonder where in your own
life is it something that's very private
to you feelings of
well because it it does go into your art
but sometimes
you know I I'm I'm very keen for people
to know that they they they shouldn't
use every joke as a window to the soul
of the comedian because sometimes I'll
I'll make a joke or or routine that is
the opposite of what I feel because it
makes the joke better and I I'm very I'm
militant about people going listen it it
it sometimes it's just it really is just
a joke and sometimes it's the opposite
of what I believe I start with my my
supernatur I do a sort of a an off color
joke and they go oh they've grown and I
go that was irony you see because that's
when I say something I don't really mean
and you as an audience laugh at the
wrong thing because you know what the
right thing is it's a way to and I sort
of and they get it and then I I call
back that sometimes I do I go no don't
let me down now remember what we said so
I'm playing with those those those
constraints and misunderstandings.
But um your first point that David Brent
um he was sort of on that cusp. I was
fascinated that that Cle did it a little
bit with with Faulty Towers
where you know it was he was
he was sort of lower middle class and
you know he wanted to uh his aspiration
was Buckingham Palace whereas by the
time I got around to doing the office
the new aspiration was Beckingham
Palace. It was that sort of level you
know what I mean? I want to be on telly
that whatever I want to be on telly I
want to be famous and it was just
creeping in then.
Um and it was a a very important part of
the office without it being a fake
documentary that is a very boring
average sitcom. There's some jokes,
there's some great performance, but if
you don't know why this man is acting
like that, you've lost 50% of what's
funny and tragic about that. And he,
you're right, he's trying to move just
like Basel faulty. He's trying to move,
right? But he's doing it for the same
reasons, right? And you all this
[__] usual. I want that. I want
this. We need that. We have to do this.
But it all comes down to one thing,
right? It's being happy. It's being
happy with yourself and having and and
then what's being happy? Well, there's
there's so many boxes to tick. And the
one people forget is worth. It's the
It's absolutely massive.
It's worth
and um so all those things went into
David Brent, but he basically needed a
hug. And I remember in the days when you
were in every paper and doing every
interview, right? You you someone said,
"What's your favorite thing?" And you
said, "Um the office." Uh, and there was
a picture of David Bent and uh, you
talked about David Bent and you said
it's beautiful. It's sad and it is. And
I I'm and by the And I remember that one
of the first times I read that someone
It is sad. Um, because he needs a hug.
That's all that's all he's doing. He's
is saying, "Am I good enough? Do you
love me yet?" And it's [__] tragic.
And when you know that, I think you like
David Ben. I think you liked him.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I always did. One of
my favorite lines. I like that. Um I was
thinking about it recently that uh
that's good that's not good news and bad
news. That's good news and irrelevant
news. There you go. That's not a phrase
though, is it?
But now but now that level of narcissism
is mediocre.
Now there now we have leaders saying
things like that. The bad news is at the
pandemic. The good news is I'm uh I'm up
three in the polls. You know, it's like
it it really and it just got worse and
worse. I had to really up my game um for
life on the road because it had been 15
years and now David Brent wasn't even
that odd or annoying compared to do you
know what I mean? People on the
apprentice who
who who say I will destroy anyone who
stands in my way. That is like an
unwritten law with the producers going,
"Let me on and I'll behave badly for Big
Brother contestants. Let me in there and
I I'll start a fight and take my clothes
off." Okay, you promise. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. With this this this
obsession with seeing normal people
destroy themselves. Some of them some of
I don't know how some of them passed the
the medical exam because some of them
they shouldn't be in there and it's not
good for them. this thing where people
keep going back to fame and going, "Do
you love me yet?" No, they don't love
you. They want you to fail. That it's
Anyway,
yeah, there's a kind of like there's
been a a glorification of idiocy in
culture and it seems like that's
something that still annoys you, that
the that sort of celebration of
stupidity. And it seems like a lot of
what you're saying it like is that
you're very a grounded person like you
said like you know my role is a jester.
I don't want to get out of my box so you
know you can tease the king but don't
start like you know trying to grab the
crown or anything. Um
yeah but like um what about like how
what is um see with the um there's two
areas I want to talk to you about. one,
your deep, deep love of animals, and
two, your obvious, very public and uh
articulate atheism. Uh, and I'll sort of
talk about how I see those things as
correlative, you know, I suppose, as we
as we go on about it. But like, um,
firstly, have you always been like that
with the animals?
Yeah. Well, that's Yeah, I mean, I don't
remember not loving animals. I mean, you
know, I was born into uh a family with
um with pets and uh uh it was all I
remember when I was uh when I was a kid,
my brother was 10 years older than me.
And um he got in trouble, right, for
punching a bloke in the park. And my all
my mom wanted of us really was to not to
go to jail or die in a barroom fight. Do
you know what I mean? That was
it was an international comedian. Just
don't die before me, you know. And um
and uh so he must have been it was he
was an adult. And uh she went, "What'd
you punch him for?" And he went, "He
kicked the dog." And my mom went, "Oh,
all right." So
that was the my first bit of, you know,
street justice. But yeah, um, you know,
my mom loves animals. We always had a
dog and a cat. And I remember five, six,
seven years old, I was just out in the
garden all the time. Just look, I was
just I was fascinated with the world. I
wanted to know everything about the
world. What what where did this um
animal evolve from? What's what's he
connected to? I I just wanted to I I
wanted it all. I mean, learn I suppose
learning was my first love, but science
and nature, I've always been fascinated
with it. I still am. Um, it's always
been a privilege. It It makes me feel
good. I don't know why an animal makes
me I'm in awe of an animal, you know,
and uh even down to, you know, um um a
cat died uh recently, but it was like if
that cat was sat on me, it's our cat,
right? We own it, right? As much as you
can. Um it was still a privilege that
that cat wanted to sit on me. I think
what a privilege that is. And and I I
can't stress enough that we're and I
know you
totally agree with this, but we're just
part of nature. We're not above it.
We're we're we're nothing special. We're
not as important as bees. We're not as
important as bees, right? Let's let's
let that thing in, you know? So yeah, I
absolutely love animal and and my my big
hate out of all of everything about, you
know, preservation and nature and this
species and that species is is still
animal cruelty. I don't get it. I don't
know why. I don't know the pleasure. I'm
worried about the psychology of people
who who you know and and there's a
there's a scale obviously there's a
weird scale from sort of serial killer
to people who just don't think they're
they're worth worrying about that much
you know um
but yeah I've never I've never it keeps
me awake it's the only thing that makes
my blood boil
and and keeps me awake at night you know
and now we've got Twitter and you do
what you can I there's Not a day go by
when someone doesn't send me something,
I go, "Oh, I wish that wasn't in my
head, but it is. So, I've got to do
something now." You know?
Yeah. Yeah. I suppose there must be like
people that don't Well, and people that
are capable of being cruel to animals,
it seems, I would guess, is a kind of
rupture between that person and their
sort of knowledge of us all sort of
feeling pain. A kind of sort of an
impeded compassion or something, an
inability to feel. I mean, there's
something Yeah, you're right. There's
something wrong with someone who who
actually enjoys seeing an animal in
pain. I mean, that is that's one end of
the scale, you know, but then there's
people in denial, you know, there's
people there's lots of propaganda out
there why it's okay, why I, you know,
why bull fighting's okay. Um, because
it's it's an honorable way for the bull
to die. Shut up. Because it's tradition.
Well, so was slavery and child
sacrifice. It's like it's cultist
culture, right? It it's like what? I
don't get it. I don't I don't get it.
And the things that then you find out
the things behind it, right? This
[__] sequ with a sword, right?
They've they've already drugged the
[__] ball. They cut the tendons on
the back of his neck. They [__] blunt
the Let's keep it fair. Let's send him
Honestly, why have you done this to me?
Why have you done
Yeah, I I don't Yeah, I don't get it.
I reckon a lot of um the problems that
we're experiencing in the world, like
right across the scope of our
conversation so far, whether it's people
craving fame, agilation, celebrity,
approval, or people being uh cruel to
animals. I I I reckon much of it can be
derived from a sense of being separate
from nature, whether that's inner nature
or outer nature. Like that people see
themselves as isolated, alienated
individuals that you they're making
their own luck in the world and live
sort of in a a world
extracted from meaning or devoid of
meaning. And this is where um I suppose
I'm interested in the way that you I I
know cuz I've listened to your stuff
like that your atheism began when you
sort of saw your mom like go don't say
that to your brother when you was like a
kid. Um about like you know as if like
and that Jesus was a sort of a kind of
baby an additional babysitter and an
omniresent sort of uh you know nanny of
the estate.
Exactly. But like but but like I spend a
cause cuz see I spend a lot of time I
suppose uh I'm solopistic narcissistic
person you know been through the mill
with addiction with fame and sex and
drugs and money and all that kind of
stuff and it's placed me in a a point
where I've had to open myself up to
different ideas. I imagine if you and I
talked about institutional or orthodox
religion and the way that it is
structured and the way that power is
deployed, prejudice enacted, violence
underwritten, I reckon we'd probably
agree. But one of the things that I feel
is that that my own love of animals and
also my cat did die last week sadly. He
was also 16 because Jenny told me um and
it like I was so affected by it. I was
more I was surprised by the amount of
grief and sadness that I felt like it
took me apart. I let it hit me full on.
We buried him in the garden. I dug a
hole. I got into it. There was only one
self-indulgent bit. Everything was
sincere except for one moment, Ricky. I
did smear soil on me face as a sort of
expression of deep grief.
Whatever gets you through.
That's what I needed to do. That's
that's just me expressing myself.
I'm done. And and I think the way you're
going is that um uh I seem a spiritual
person, but not literally. And that's
totally true that I I I'm in as much awe
at seeing a tree or a mountain or a bird
or a river as anyone who thinks God made
it. I I am in I I see the beauty of
nature. And I think most and I I don't I
don't know this, but you're right.
There's a huge difference between
spirituality, there's something to the
south that gets you through that you
that you want to you want to know the
reason. You want to connect all those
things. I feel all those things without
without the belief in a god or gods.
Religion is something else. Religion
religion basically says you you want to
get into heaven. I know I know him. You
just got to do this [__] for me and
we're called.
You know, we we know that that
everything that's ever started was was
was written by usually a man with an
agenda. You know, it's like it's no
coincidence all those rules in the Old
Testament sort of favor certain men in
the c there's no it's not a coincidence,
you know, and and the same with, you
know, it's a it's no coincidence that if
you're born in America, you're probably
Christian. If you're born in India,
probably a Hindu, etc., etc. We know
that. But if we're talking about
spirituality, um, uh, I'm all for it.
It's never bothered me. It's ne someone
belief in God has never bothered me.
It's, what do you do with it? If you
start saying to me, I, you know, um, I
love this prophet or that prophet and I
love God. I go, good, fine. Yeah. And I
do this and I believe, oh, great. Yeah,
put it. And I think we should throw
homosexuals off buildings. Well, no.
Now, now we got Now we got to talk. Now
we've got to talk right just you know um
so it's when there's suddenly an agenda
that that coincidentally favors the
person you know it's when people have
exactly luckily God agrees with them
there
I absolutely and um and I think it was
started with good intentions um in the
invention of lion when my character
invents religion he does it because he
can't stand his mom's fear of death. And
and I remember when my mom was dying, if
she asked me, I was thinking I was going
to lie. I was like, "Yeah, there
probably is." Because if that, you know,
I I probably would have. So, um uh I
think people there's so many myths about
atheism. We can go into the the
definitions and all that, but I think
it's worse. People think that atheists
run into churches and ruin people's
days. You know, it's all parked. It's
nothing spread the truth. I um people
ask me, "Have you ever been in a
church?" I go, "Yeah, yeah, it's lovely
buildings. I love them. What do you
mean?" You know, it it's this I don't I
don't know where it comes from. And
also,
technically, atheism doesn't even mean
uh you you don't believe in God. It
means that sorry, you believe there's no
God. It means that you just haven't
found God yet. You you know, there's no
evidence.
that that is true but it's you know core
and I've explained this many times that
technically I'm an agnostic atheist
because one deals with knowledge and one
deals um with belief so no one knows if
we agree that that no one knows we're
all atheists so now what do you think
and believers say I think there is a god
and atheist think I don't think there is
a god because I haven't got any evidence
yet so that is all is all All I'm saying
um as you say, religion is something
else to belief in spirituality and um
you know uh uh
and people even say to me um if someone
proved there was a god would you
believe? I go well of course I would
it wouldn't even be belief. It would be
knowledge. You know it would also be the
greatest discovery ever. Forget let's
cancel the Nobel site from now on. He's
discovered God. That's it's done. And I
think if if it, you know, um that would
change everything, I think. Uh but until
we know, I I just don't I I don't want
to live my life
um uh by a belief in something that I
have no evidence in. That's all that's
that's all I'm saying. And I and I
sometimes say to people that, you know,
um uh a a a good Christian or a good
Muslim or a good Jew or whatever is
someone who does all the good bits in
that holy book and ignores the bad bits.
And I say, if you already know right
from wrong, you don't need the book. And
and and you know, you have to
cherrypick. Um and uh we know that the
bad believers are the ones that do the
bad bits, too, you know. Um, so for me
it's it's it is personal. I just happen
not to believe in God. I used to, but
now I've thought about it and I I feel I
don't need a God. Um, but the the the
thing that I really object to is people
assuming that you can't be a good person
if you don't believe in a god, which
which is proved over and over again. And
I've tweeted things um like um uh there
are good atheists and bad atheists.
There are good Christians and bad
Christians and that God has never
changed that. And all I'm saying is I
get it. It doesn't this is not me go. It
works both ways. You shouldn't judge
people by the beliefs. You should judge
them by their actual behavior. You know,
right and wrong. You know, some people
believe the right thing but don't do the
right thing. and vice versa. And I I
just think I feel I don't need it. I
just don't need a structured guide book
outside at you know my own morality. And
morality is relative and not absolute.
And you you'd have to keep dogma is the
problem. I think dogma is the real
problem. And it's not just in religion
anymore. It's creeping into everything.
It's creeping into politics and it's
creep you know identity politics. It's
creeping into um just social um
structures and opinions. It's it's you
know if anyone says to me this is what
shouldn't be questioned. [__] that. No,
let's um No. No. Let's question it.
That's a red to a ball. You know what?
Don't I've always been like that. I've
always got teachers said that I I'll
always even a board game I think what
are the rules? Can I can I get how do I
win within the rules?
Yeah,
I've gone on sort of like the opposite
journey in that I feel like I started
off atheistic just the same way that I
would reject any attempt to impose
regulation or control on me for the
purposes of domination and but as I've
you know gone through my own stuff with
you know addiction and mental health or
whatever it is and and like I know that
you're very um like you know that for
example afterlife is about legitimate
grief as opposed to some kind of
abstract idea of mental illness brought
about by hormonal or neurological
balance. But myself, my own sense of
despair, particularly looking at it from
a perspective of mental health issues
and addiction is that there is an
unadressed yearning for a kind of
oneness, togetherness and and like you
know to to your point earlier about
Brent in indeed for love. And when like
you talk about that sense of awe of uh
like the appreciation of an animal, the
love of an animal and the sort of regard
and gratitude for having an animal love
you and care for you or the beauty of
nature or the deep deep beauty of the
cosmos, what I feel like and my own
appreciation, understanding, stroke
belief in God is is that there is a kind
of in the love of it, in the awareness
of rightness itself, there is an
indication that there is such a thing as
rightness. Not that there any one
particular group or ideology has unique
a particular and special access to it
and and I really firmly deeply believe
that spirituality is for me not for me
to tell other people I don't reckon you
should be gay or I don't reckon you
should be allowed to do like I feel like
it's I do my
Bible in the Bible it says you should
pray secretly.
Oh wow.
So yeah.
Yeah. Like there is something sort of
deeply private about it. But I also
think Ricky that there is a social
consequence to um I don't necessarily
want to say atheism because I completely
agree with your point that there's good
and bad you know in like beyond those
kind of limited taxonomies but like I do
feel like when people think there's no
purpose or meaning that and that needn't
necessarily be just because of a belief
in God that it creates cultures that are
oddly materialistic nihilistic and I
feel that in the last 20 years we're
seeing more and more worship of self,
worship of individuals.
Well, of course, there's a new
narcissism, of course, and that and um I
I don't know why. I think social media
is is is partly to blame. I think people
being rewarded
for bad behavior is partly to blame. You
know, magazines or TV or whatever. You
know, I did a speech in the Big Brother
House as Andy Milman in Extras and uh
again, that was at the that was at the
beginning of it and and now it's got
worse. But um couple of points I I do
think there's a people crave the
oneness. Um even if we don't go about
understanding about why are we here
because again that's very human. We're
inquisitive. We want to know why. We
want the answer why. And some people
don't accept we don't know yet but we're
on the way. They don't. They go no
that's no you know the god of the gaps.
We we we understand that. Well if I if
you don't know explain it god did it.
Okay. It doesn't really solve anything.
even down to the I put a joke in
afterlife where cats bothering me and
she says uh how did it all come from
somewhere from nothing and uh I go well
uh where did it all come from then god
made it I go okay where did come from
she went he's always been around I go
simple as that in it so you know it it
doesn't answer the question but I get it
and I think I think
um apart from people wanting there to be
some sort of um divine justice because
you know that that would be great. Good
people would be rewarded and bad people
would be punished. Brilliant. Okay. It
it doesn't work like that. You know, you
only have to look at um you know,
children in Africa being born with
cancer and you know, we we know that's
not we know mysterious ways isn't an
explanation. Okay. Um uh that that to me
is someone who doesn't know the answer
and says mysterious ways. But apart from
that, you're right. We're seeking the
answer. Why are we here? Um I think we
think that hold on. Well, it's too good.
It's too good to be chance. It's
everything's perfect. Well, it seems
that way, you know. It's like Douglas
Adams puddle, you know, when it imagines
this I fit this hole perfectly. Um uh
but I think you're right. We we are
scared and alone and
we the the the idea of death is is
horrible. What? You'll never exist
again. What was the point? Um and again
I I talk about this in uh in afterlife
one where I I say um um Kath's saying
that uh if if you think it's you know um
there's no heaven, why don't you kill
yourself? And I say, "So if you're
watching a really good film, but you
know it's going to end, you might as
well just stop it." She went, "No,
because I'm going to watch it again."
And I say, "I think that's the amazing
thing about life. You can't watch it
again. You know, one day you'll hug, you
know, your your mom for the last time.
You'll smell your last flower. You'll
eat your last meal. You won't know it's
your last, but it will be your last. And
so you got to make the most of
everything. And it is a terrifying
prospect. It is quite sad that you we'll
never exist again. I I think but it
doesn't mean it's not true. You know,
the bottom line is I can't believe
something I don't believe. And so, how
do I find meaning? Well, we are here. We
are here. The chances of us being us,
you being you and me being me existing
now, that sperm hitting that egg is 400
trillion to one. You know, we're not
special, but we are lucky. We do exist.
It's incredible. And I think of it, it's
like a holiday. We don't exist for 13
and a half billion years. Then we we we
explode into this mass this electronic
blob of thought, introspection, love,
hate, fear, beauty,
horror for 80, 90, 100 years if we're
lucky. Then we die and we never exist
again. We return, our atoms return and
it carries on, right? And that's not
scary because I think people are scared
of death because they don't know what's
beyond. And someone said to me, what do
you what do you think it feels like when
you die? And I say like the 13 and a
half billion years before I was born.
And that was all right.
So, but
we but the big thing is injecting
meaning. I think you're totally right. I
think you're totally right. When you
start thinking about it, why are we
here? Well,
um I mean, not even the how, but why?
Well, to live your life to the fullest
and not and not hurt anyone. To leave
the world in a better place than it was
when you came into it. to to experience
everything. All the reasons, all the
obvious reasons, you know, love, wine,
dogs, learning, um, all these great
things that you can do every minute of
every day that you're alive and then you
then you check out, you go, I'm done.
Thanks. And it's and it's done. And it's
beautiful. It's [__] beautiful.
It is beautiful. But I was struck when
you said that by a few things. One is
like this of like the injection of
meaning as in you know like meaning
would have to be imported externally
fabricated somehow invented whereas I
think on some level I feel that there is
that meaning is inhered and that that
the meaning is in the kind of zeal that
you have when you describe the things
that give you love pleasure um you know
connection whether it's wine or dogs or
whatever. I I I I I've had like some
some experiences like through meditation
and when I I took drugs too young and
now so I'm now I'm not allowed to do Ica
or LSD or them things I would definitely
be doing if I wasn't in recovery. But I
had like those of these experiences that
were a kind of I would say a sort of an
evaporation of self and yet a continued
awareness. I know that my consciousness
is connected to my biology but I have a
sense somewhat derived from uh the sort
of the fact that you know you can't
trace how um you know mechanical parts
ever become conscious that consciousness
may be elemental somehow. Now, that like
that doesn't point to a god in a
traditional patriarchal or doineering
sense, but it sort of points to an a an
element that's very difficult to
quantify. Whether that's the deep
intelligence of nature, the deep
mathematics of biochemistry and biology,
biology, and the essential mystery of
consciousness itself, you know, commonly
referred to as the the hard problem. And
through these sort of individual
experiences, whilst I've not had
anything that you would call typically
religious, Jesus emerging out of a
tunnel, Ganesha lashing around or any of
that sort of stuff, what I've had is
like a well, it's highly bloody
interpretive cuz say there's this one
breath thing I do. You breathe, you
breathe from the abdomen very
aggressively and then you sort of take a
sharp inhale and you normally you're
nearly well a medical man would say what
you're doing there is hyperventilating
and nearly passing out. But from the
inside, what it feels like is bloody
hell. For this moment, I'm aware and I
am not me. What is this? What is this?
Is there a possibility that my
awareness, your awareness, the awareness
of all animals and a and and an
awareness that's impossible to read is
somehow present in all nature, in all
matter? And if that's true, then there's
a kind of a real a genuine cohesion and
togetherness between all of the beings
of the earth and beyond. And like and
those people that can't actually enjoy
the lives that we are privileged to have
of the red wine or the dogs or whatever
like I'm not saying that's some sort of
comfort to them but in fact those of us
that are in privileged position might
feel newly incentivized to work towards
a different kind of society and system
that is more reflective of those values.
Now that doesn't necessarily require
monotheism, pantheonism or any of those
things, but it is somewhat underwritten
by a kind of a sameness or and a oneness
and how that might relate to justice.
And also there is a sort of a a personal
experience of mystery in it. I wonder
what you feel about that and if you're
curious about psychedelics and that and
awkward states and that.
Uh well um you know I love I love a good
mystery and you're right. Um it is a
mystery. Science, all science it does is
is it's a discipline that follows the
evidence. And what science keeps saying
and some people say this is a flaw, but
it's been wrong before. Well, science
never been wrong before. Our
interpretation science has been wrong
for you know it it science is just a is
a way to look and understand the the
physical um universe. And what science
says, it keeps saying, "Okay, this is
the least wrong theory we've got so
far." And then the next day it goes,
"Okay, we're even less wrong today. We
were we were less wrong today." You
know, they've mapped the beginning of
the universe to to a fraction of a
second, which is pretty close. But um so
uh I I think science
keeps proving itself and over and over
again. and and the fact that we don't
understand you know the mind body
problem completely yet. Um that is the
beauty and the more we understand the
more questions it throws up. It's like
um you know people saying the missing
link uh like there's there's there's
there's there's this fossil and there's
this fossil and uh we find that one and
people go no there's two missing links
so you can't win you know and um all
science keep doing is just keep filling
the gaps and finding and finding new
gaps. Um but yeah, you're right. You
know, I I I think that
um it is. It is. It's amazing what
intelligence is, what you know, I'm a
determinist, which change is nothing. I
I I believe that free free will is an
illusion. So be it. If it feels like it,
it might as well be. Um but then to
analyze it and go, well, you know, uh
we're we're machines. We we are
machines.
Um, we we're machines trying to
understand ourselves and that's hard.
Will will there one day be a computer
that is suffering from anxiety? I reckon
so.
I reckon so. I reckon there be a genius
computer that's worried about [__] I
really do.
Yeah, that's the
We're We're lumps of meat. We're We're
chimps. with brains the size of a
planet. Of course we go mad and try and
kill each other and worry about what's
the point. Of course we do. It's it's
overwhelming. And the more you think
about it, the more frightening it is. So
um it it I just think that
um you know my new my new show
Supernatural I start with saying it's
called Supernature for two reasons. One
I want to debunk the supernatural. I
don't believe in anything supernatural.
I think that anything that that exists
is by definition part of nature and is
explainable. If not now, then
eventually. And also super nature cuz
nature is super enough. We don't need
angels in unicorns. We've got the
[__] octopus. And then I go into, you
know, we don't we don't need to look I
feel we don't need to look elsewhere.
That doesn't mean I'm not in awe of
poetry and intelligence. And you know, I
I just don't think that unweaving
the rainbow spoils it. I think it makes
it more exciting. When I see when I see
a card trick and I don't know how it's
done and then the musician tells me, I
can't wait for him to show someone else
who doesn't know how it's done. And how
it's done is more exciting for me. just
do do you know what I mean?
Yes. Yes, I do. And and I also sort of
don't believe in magic and you know that
that kind of stuff. I but one of the
things I spoke to Neil deGrasse Tyson
about was uh yeah that dude he's amazing
isn't he? Like I spoke to him about the
sort of
quantum physics all bets are off. We can
we can talk like this till we're blue in
the face and then quantum physics comes
along and
there's that saying if you think you
understand quantum physics you don't
understand quantum physics.
Yeah.
It's magic. It might quantum physics by
all our definitions of science and
nature. Right. And we're intelligent
people. We've read of it. We think,
right? We've got a good brain. We got as
good a brain as anyone. But [__] quantum
physics, it's mental.
Yes. Yes. It sort of seems what I like
that came up in our conversation and I
sort of used it to illustrate my feeling
that the the limitations of our senses
and the limit and our and the
limitations of our capacity to handle
knowledge mean that there will always be
a realm beyond knowledge. that all
scientific disciplines are contingent
upon ampl amplification of existing
senses microscopic telescopic even hu
calculating devices like AI uh and that
that the the the the
I re I don't see like quantum physics as
woo type magic but I do see it as an
indication of [__] hell there is an
intelligence at work
it's just we can't you know like some
people say You can't understand it like
God can understand it. You haven't got
God's brain. Well, that is quantum
physics to me. You know, the fact that
it's it happens means it exists and it's
true and it's scientific.
But then to ask us to understand it now,
we've we've that's a big ask cuz it's
it's incredible just the uncertainty
principle. The fact that I want it to be
metaphor. I want it to go we don't
literally mean it's in two places at
once. I go, "Yeah, we do." is the way
that times were. Right. Start again.
Right. Right. I've got two potatoes.
It's it's because
Yeah. It's it's a and usually it's the
scale of things that we can't fathom,
you know. Um but it doesn't mean it's
not true. And if it's true, if it's
true, it's real. It It's as simple as
that for me. And and I know that that
sounds like that sounds like a
linguistic trick for me to get away
without actually feeling that I
understand it.
But it doesn't make it not true. And
that's all I think. The fact that I
don't understand something doesn't mean
it's not understandable. I wouldn't be
so arrogant as to think that because I
don't understand
um uh consciousness and the fact that
the universe is expanding, it doesn't
mean it's not true. Um so I think I've
always got that get out clause. I don't
have to leap for a being did it. A
different being on a different plane and
level made it. I don't I that's all I
don't know. And I think that most people
would be satisfied if you sat him down
and said all those things that you think
God did. Right. He did.
He just doesn't have a will like you
think he does. He's just nature.
Yes.
And I think some people would be happy
with that. I think
yes. Because will is like you know if as
much as I can understand it strongly
related to my individual imperatives
which are based on survival which are
therefore material need to procreate
need to have food need to have shelter
need to die. So will however it might
refract through a culture that no longer
requires of me that I seek shelter or
find food you know like all our all
culture is coming from this place. And I
think when we're talking about the
absolute whether we're talking about it
in sort of materialistic scientific
terms or spiritual or even religious
terms, it's not going to be something
that we can comprehend and understand.
And I've always used that as a kind of
rebuttal to the idea of why do bad
things happen? Because I feel like in
this we are on such a narrow bandwidth
of all potential realities of all
potential understandable forms and and
unfor
notions of good and bad are inhibited.
We are that we are beyond that.
Yes. Well, this is another point again.
And I put it in I put it in afterlife as
a bit of a joke where Kath says to me if
we if you don't believe in God and
heaven all that why don't you just go
out raping and murdering as much as you
want and I say I do. I do which is not
at all. And that's a scary prospect that
some people because they think an
absolute morality they think that
there's no point in being good without a
god. And that's a that's a big that's
quite a big school of thought that
people take that to the nth degree. They
go, you know, and and my my worry is
that if you're only not murdering cuz
you think God's watching,
that's that's scary.
Yeah. Like it's the purge,
you know, if if that's what stops you
murdering, then Yeah. Okay. That's
that's whatever whatever gets you
through. Um, so yeah, I I don't believe
in absolute morality because I think
that we invented morality as as a code
to live by so we could all be as happy
as possible. Um, and you know, there
there are different laws for different
times and different species. You know,
the the the law of the spider is not the
same as the law of as the human. We know
that if I'm starving, I don't eat my own
legs. and and when we make we don't bite
the head of the partner afterwards. So
it it's a nonsense to to to try and
equate a morality with with with nature
and and spirituality and religion. It it
is because people got together and
decided that the best way to live, you
know, that's that's that's society more
than anything. and and and morality
existed before any god in my opinion
before any god you know and they they
just took the golden rule which I love I
love but it's not religion that you know
do as you would be done by and I think
it's a it's it's it's it's a it's a
really good rule of thumb and it would
and if everyone did that the world would
instantly be a better place um w-
without without any god interference and
the other one that I've come to love
Probably my favorite piece from the
Bible that everyone's forgotten and I
see it more and more in the last 10-15
years and particularly on social media
is
let
um those amongst you who is without sin
cast the first stone. And I tell you
that shut that would shut so many
[__] people up. you know, despite
what people think of me, I'm not a very
judgmental person in my private. I'm I I
go whatever, you know, good good luck to
them. I mean, I I always try and see I
even try and empathize with what you'd
call bad people. I think why do they do
that? I I'm always willing to I' I'd be
a judge going promise you won't do it
again. You know, I would Okay, let you
know what I mean. I I really do think
you know one one uh better a thousand
guilty go free than one innocent person,
you know. Um but
um
we do have to we do have to have these
societal laws for the benefit of
everyone. And and and the irony is that
a secular society would defend all
rights to religious belief more than any
one religion does.
Um, but it's all it's saying is let's
not make it law. Let's not make
superstition law. Let's not And it's so
funny. I see it. I see the I see the
hypocrisy in a so-called
Christian um country, free country who
who hate the idea of this this
fundamentalist state, but they're doing
the same. It's just that there's a
different God they're doing it with.
It's you're the same. you're the same.
You think God is on your side and you
can you can you know your tribe can
rule. So yeah I you know unlike all
religions I I I treat all religions
equally.
Yes. Um what about though secularism is
some degree underwritten by economic
ideologies and I I would say sort of
social systems that in a way behave
precisely as religions do in that they
inhibit imp I I don't agree with that at
all because all secularism says that we
want to we want to separate church from
state that you know you don't you don't
base any laws on a particular belief in
a particular god or religion you know
that that's that's all it's really
saying, isn't it? It and you know what
in in the the the freest most liberal um
sensible site is it it is secular really
but some people go to church and that's
fine.
Doesn't bother anyone. But on a on a on
a
on a a a an exam with biology, physics,
and chemistry, the answer isn't God did
it. That's all. That's all a secular
society insist. You know, this works.
Biology works. Physics works. I It works
over and over again. Um it's it's just
it's just induction. Um, but I I would
said, um, if you could, would you ban
religion? I go, "No, I I I honestly
wouldn't. I honestly wouldn't ban
religion." In fact, if someone started
banning someone the right to believe in
whatever god, I'd march going, "Let them
believe in that God." It's your right to
believe in whatever. I I honestly I'd
fight for anyone's right to believe in
in God, goblins, witches, you know, just
don't throw homosexuals off buildings
and we're fine.
Yeah.
I think in the end it becomes God and
good become synonymous in any meaningful
ideology that that there is a kind of
sense of harmony and as best possible
fairness and non-invention.
Well, it's all it's it's all I've got.
You know, I've lost the working class
thing now. So all I've got is um atheism
as my oppression. There's 13 countries
where I'd be put to death. And in
America, we were voted least trustworthy
group along with rapists. So I've always
got a I'm oppressed, Russell.
In that case, I'm on your side.
Yeah.
Oh, wicked. Ricky, we done an hour
there, mate. That's an
Wow, it's my nap time.
Yeah, that's You can go back into your
carefully guarded rituals of soup and
whatever else it is that holds you
together in your godless, nihilistic
expanse.
Well, I'd just like to say I give you
the compliment. I'm so It's so lovely to
see you well and
all grown up, not sitting there in a
sheet, but in real proper clothes. And I
I couldn't be prouder.
Oh, that's lovely. Thank you, mate.
That's a I will uh I carry that. Thanks,
man.
Thank you very much. If you enjoyed that
conversation, go over to
luminarypodcast.com
now and sign up for a week's free trial
and listen to the many, many fantastic
conversations that I've had on this
platform. Simon Amto being but one of
them. Who did we do recently that I was
well into? David Eagleman, absolutely
fantastic.
Frankie Bole, there's just so many
brilliant conversations. All right, lots
of love. Glad you enjoyed it. Thanks for
tuning in.